hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and today in Spring boot we
are going to complete this spring aop so
I'm taking it Mark let's start with
aspect oriented programming which is aop
and that is being used by many other
topics which we are going to cover like
transactional okay that's why I wanted
to cover it before so in simple term
if you want to explain aop we can say
that it helps to intercept the method
invocation right and we can perform some
tasks before and after the
method okay so what aop says that hey
you allow it allow us to focus on
business logic by handling boilerplate
and repetitive code like logging
transaction management Etc what I mean
to say here is let's say you want to
have certain business logic like this is
your current business logic but many
times there are certain piece of code
which we have to write let's say you
have to keep logging certain things you
have to keep logging after your business
logic runs and also transaction you have
to start transaction you have to end the
transaction and if some uh issue comes
you have to roll back okay so there are
few things which is apart from from your
business logic that is known as
boilerplate means which you have to do
and these are repetitive means it is not
just for one one class or one method if
you have 100 methods which required
logging you have to do the same thing if
you have 100 method which requir
transactional property you have to start
and end the transaction roll back all
these things so these are repetitive
code in your
business uh repo so that's where aop
says that hey you focus on business
business logic this boiler plate and
repetitive code I will take care of it
so you don't need to handle put it over
here you can remove logging and
transaction roll back all you have is
now your business logic and somehow this
logging transaction management aop will
take care of it how we will see
that so aspect so when we says that
aspect oriented programming what is
aspect means as p is a module which
handles this repetitive and Boiler code
so I told you right this repetitive and
Boiler code like logging and all
transaction uh commands and all these
are repetitive and Boiler code so all
this logic can go to a particular place
that we call generally an
aspect so what does it helps it helps in
achieving the reusability and
maintainability of the code definitely
so now in this aspect let's say we have
put
logging now if even at 100 places you
want to put uh the log right you don't
have to write the same logic again and
again at 100 places uh in your main Core
Business Place you don't even have to
write it aop will automatically take
care of putting the logging either you
want before or after or both right so
all the 100 places can use this
code right so if it helps in achieving
the reusability and the maintainability
of the code so only one place is where
it has to maintain and any changes made
it here all 100 places will get impacted
with that so maintainability is
easy so dependency so before we start
using aop this dep uh this dependency we
have to add into our pal. XML so you can
add this dependency in your form okay
spring hyphen boot hyphen starter hyphen
aop okay this is very very simple
example when I'm showing you the demo
like what exactly it does but don't
worry about this uh whatever you see
here right at the rate expect at the r
before don't worry about it at all it
just want to show you that when I told
you it helps to intercept the method
what exactly it is so now let's say that
this is one of my class now in this
class this is a rest controller class
where I have exposed an uh rest API like
path this fetch employ /
API slash fetch employe I have exposed
like
this now here if you see that I am just
returning item fetch so this is my
business logic this is my business logic
but I wanted
something
before it return before this method get
executed I have to perform certain task
so what happen is I have here if you see
you won't see
anything but this is one aspect I
created in that I have written one
method don't worry about all these
things how this I have written one
method which does something let's say
logging consider this is it is is
logging consider this system. print
Talent is at I am
logging so I am just logging that hey I
am inside this before method
aspect okay now I started the
application so here if you see
application started
properly now I am hitting the request
that in the Local Host I am hitting this
API fetch employ
now before the invocation of this before
the execution of this method what would
happen is this before method will get
invoke so this will logging will happen
inside before method aspect so here if
you see it will first print inside
before method
aspect after this it will return the
item fetch it after this it will return
the item
fetch okay so this is what I mean to say
when I say that aop helps you to
intercept the method right so before
this method get invoked it intercepted
it it performs certain
task right and then it calls the method
then this method Works happen and if
there is something after you have to
do so there is uh you can also perform
certain task after this method execution
also now the main thing what exactly how
it is happened how this interception
happen how this interception internally
works right so now we all have to
understand that
part now let's slowly goes to each and
every part of it
okay if you don't understand in a single
shot please check it again I will try to
go slow because this is lot of things
going to come into
this okay okay so first thing
first the aspect class where we are
going to write our Boiler code
right we have to annotate that class
with ad theate
aspect okay this aspect has certain
purpose so spring boot get to know that
okay this logging aspect because this is
at theate component when you start an
application right spring boot scans so
when spring boot find this
hey this is this class is annotated with
at the rate aspect then spring boot
knows that okay what does it contain it
it contains certain
methods which might require
interception right which might need to
be get executed before certain method or
after certain
method so now here if you see that the
first part is your point
cut so this annotation here if you see
this before this method I have put this
at theate before and there is certain
expression so this expression this
expression this expression is known as
point cut what what point cut is it's an
expression which tell where an advice
should be applied advice is what advice
is this method actually
this method plus
this before or
after Okay so this point cut what happen
is it matches it do some matching logic
that okay this class this class and
inside this class this
method okay some matching happened okay
for this method I have to do some
interception means before this method
actually get invoked I have to run this
whether before or after this will tell
whether before I have to run or after I
have to run okay but how to find out
which method we have to run this code
whether before or
after it is tell by point cut how to
identify that particular class or
particular method where we have to run
this piece of code is tell by point
cut so now let's go through this
expression
one by one there okay so now we are
going to this point cut we are going
deep into this point cut now so point
cut definition now you already know it's
an expression which tell where an advice
should be applied
okay this is what actually is an advice
what actually the code has to run before
the method and after the method but this
is what point cut actually
tells which for which method this has
has to be done so type of Point C so
first is
execution so here if you see that in the
execution what it says that matches a
particular method in a particular class
it matches a particular method in a
particular class so with this execution
here if you see that we have to give
expression like this so this expression
has certain part the first part is is
your access
modifier whether it's public private
protected what right and this is
optional this is
optional means even if you remove it
doesn't
matter it will check for all it will
check for private public protected all
okay so this is
optional and this is your exis
modifier the second part this is your
return type method return
type okay so whatever the return type of
your method you will write here and this
is not like an optional you can skip it
you have to provide it
okay and the third part is
your the path for your method so this is
your package com do concept and coding
do learning springbot right this is your
package this is a class name and inside
this class name this is a
method so the full method the class path
has been
given com. concept coding. learning
springboard do employ do method name
fetch
employe okay and this method doesn't
have any parameters so that's why it is
empty otherwise inside this we can
provide the parameters whether it takes
a string in some object object and all
so but here in our
example in this case if you see this
fetch
employee this has no arguments so that's
why I have kept it empty
also okay so
here so this one you got it right
execution what execution it it's always
focus on whenever you are using this
type of point cut execution
it always focus on try to match a
particular method in a particular class
right and you have to give this
way okay now there are a wild card which
we can use so there are two type of wild
card whether using star or dot
dot okay so let's see that if we want to
use a wild card how we can do it so
let's say that we want to use a star so
star means it matches any single item
now let's so now let's say this is the
class now I want to use this wild card
how to use any wild card like matches
any single item now let's say I'm
writing an execution means this type of
point cut means I have to point to a
specific method where this method has to
be run right so matching this is the
matching logic so first I use star so
now here if you see that I have removed
this because this is optional this is
not even required if you don't write it
it will check for public private
protected all type of exess modifier so
I started with this return type so
return type instead of string now I give
estess so no
matter a string or int or any object
doesn't matter
so this is one wild card now I provide
the total class for for my method
employ then this method name that before
uh uh for this method I have to do some
interception and this doesn't accept any
argument so I have kept it
empty okay so this what would happen is
so now spring boot will match this point
cut expression with this
method right and it able to identify
that okay for this method I have
to run this advice run this method now
whether before or after we will come to
that later but at least now it filter
out that okay this
is this method
is matched with this point cut
okay now the second matches any method
with single parameter string so now here
if you see that I am trying to do an
execution means again one direct
particular method it have we have to
point out star it started with the star
space so means this is the return type
whatever the return type could be a
string integer doesn't matter com do
concept and coding do learning is spring
boot. employer so this is still I have
provided a particular class now what is
the method do star now doesn't matter
whether fetch employee or you can say
that
in uh some update
employee update
employee so this star means any method
any method name now I haven't provided
any specific method name I provided star
means any method name return type also
Al I have used a star so doesn't matter
whether it's string or int So currently
till now matching is happening now in
the parameter I have given a string so
means method should have taken an string
so let's say one argument is a string
well so now the matching will not happen
for this because okay return time
matching because this is a star wild
card so this is okay fetch method okay
because this is method is star any
method name could be there but matching
is like the method should have argument
one one argument should be string does
it have any argument no this method has
any argument yes so this got matched
with this this point could get matched
to this
method so now whenever somebody try to
invoke this
method this will run either before or
after we will see
later one more example of execution
which I want to give so I'm running an
execution now a string specifically now
I'm giving that return type should be
string this should be the method
specific I have provided the exact part
to this method and also return type I
have given is
star star means single should get match
right I told you star me match any
single item so even though there so this
doesn't take any method any argument
this fetch employer doesn't take any
argument so it will not match because it
is expecting one argument either a
string either in either object doesn't
matter but when we have put a star means
at least one should be there so this
matching will not
happen Okay so now you okay so now you
understand this uh star Wild Card Asis
wild card now I'll tell you about the
second Wild Card dot dot so it matches
zero or more item mean zero or
more so first example which I am giving
you what is this it matches the fetch
employe method that take zero or more
parameter so read this execution means I
have to provide one specific method
matching return type is a string this is
the class path exactly for the
particular method so this is my package
this is my class and this is my method
name okay so till now I have provided
fully now here if you see that in the
arguments I have put dot dot
means either this fetch employe have
zero argument or more than like more
than zero like or more item it will get
matched so now in this case this got
match with
that right so let me copy it here so
that it would be easy
easy so now here if you see that even
the fetch employee has zero arguments it
will get match because dot dot means
zero or
more now see the second example of uh
this one I am running an execution means
a specific class method I have to
provide
execution a string this is a return
type com do concept and coding do dot
now here dot dot means any package any
subpackage right and ultimately this is
the method name I have provided so now
com do concept and coding dot like
whatever the package subpackage would be
in any package sub package and whatever
the classes it has if any method name is
fetch
employee within this concept and coding
package and it's package if any method
has fetch employee matching should have
happened with
that
okay now there is one more thing I want
to show that execution a string this is
a return type com do concept and coding
dot dot means concept and
coding and this package and inside this
any other package is required so it will
look for all uh this package and all
other sub
packages right all the classes inside
that all the classes inside this sub
packages also and which method I have
put a
star like doesn't matter uh so all the
methods inside the package and sub
packages of
this this match point cut should get
match
okay so
execution execution now you know this
now let's say second type of point cut
is
within now within so what within says
that matches all method within any class
or
package how now let's say I want to run
all the methods for within a class we
can do it through execution also I told
you right through execution also we can
run this way but there is a simpler way
with the within also so here here if you
see within so this is another type of
Point cod in this within there is
nothing like a return type because we
are not specifically pointing to a
method now we are giving here either the
class path or the package path com do
concept and coding. learning springbot
do employe so I have provided a
particular class so all the methods with
within a within this
class this point cut will get
match right if this
employee if this employee class
has four
methods right so this point cut will
match for all
four okay so no matter if you are
calling this method then also this
matching will happen and whatever the
advice we have to
run like below this whatever the method
we will write it will get
run now if you want to run on a package
we can say that within com. concept and
coding learning is spring boot dot dot
right and estess no matter any
class now learning a springbot package
or below sub
packages any class which is present
inside this package and sub packages for
that this point cut will get
match within point
cut there is one point cut called at the
rate within so whenever we use at the
rate right so at the rate within
means here we have to provide an
annotation we don't have to provide a
class path of a particular class we have
to provide Prov an
annotation okay matches any method in a
class right which has this annotation So
within you already know that within
works on a class level right so when we
use atate within
means any class which this annotation
which has this
annotation this point cut will
match okay so here is if you see this
example I have written one simple class
rest
controller where this is one method
which has exposed this API / fetch
employee now this fetch employee is just
calling one utility class employee util
I have autoed it employee helper method
certain helper method now this employee
util class I have put at theate
service okay and this is one method
employee helper
method so this will print this and after
that it will return item fetch so very
very simple this two classes are very
very simple it's just my business logic
I have used now I have put this aspect
class where I want to do something
before a particular method invoke so I
have put add
within okay within means targeting to a
specific class but at the rate is like I
have to provide The annotation
here I have put this
service annotation path okay so now what
is springboard will know that okay any
class which has this
annotation right all its method this
match will
happen I have
invoked this API fetch
employee now when this API is invoked
what would happen
is currently any aspect match currently
any any point cut match with this no So
currently atate within is any class
which has service annotation this class
employee has service annotation no so
there is no matching happen now it
proceed and it calls employ U employ
helper method now it is trying to invoke
this now springb say that okay this
method before I invoke this method is
there anything I have to do now it will
see that okay there is some aspect
present at theate within the class any
class which has this annotation at
theate service okay this class has this
annotation okay means this got match up
this point cut will get match up
means this method has to be run before
or after So currently we are telling
before so before this method execution
this will run inside before method
aspect so it will print inside before
method aspect and after that it will go
inside this and it print employe helper
method call employee helper method call
and after that it will put item fetch to
the
UI okay you got atate within So within
this deal with the classes all the
methods within a
classes but when we have put add theate
means it has we have to give annotation
all classes which has this
annotations okay now another type of
point cut is ADD theate annotation now
this deals with the meth method matches
any method that is annotated with given
annotation okay so here see this one I
have written one aspect class put at
theate
aspect right this is also have to use at
the at theate component because this has
to be otherwise spring board will not
manage it so we have to use at theate
component also because this is also a
bean object this
required so I am using the point type is
at theate annotation what does at theate
annotation is so we are using at theate
means right we have to provide some
annotation path so what annotation path
I have given get mapping this annotation
path I have
provided okay so what ad theate
annotation is that matches any method
that is annotated with given
annotation okay so now what would happen
is I invoke this method when I invoke
this method fetch employee is springbot
before running this method it sees that
hey any aspect is which is getting match
any point cut which is matching it will
see that okay at theate annotation is
there which says that any method which
has G mapping annotation yes it has G
mapping annotation this method has G
mapping annotation means this has to be
run before or after currently I'm
telling it at theate before if I want to
run I can tell at the rate after if I
want to run after this method So
currently I'm telling is at theate
before so means it will run first inside
before method aspect and then it will go
inside this and return this item
fetch so you got it at theate
annotation then there is something
called
ARS matches any
method with particular argument
so now here if you see this is another
point cut type where this is like a AR
GS ask and inside this like you want to
give like any method which takes this
type of argument a string comma int so
first is a string second is in so here
if you see
this
asks a string comma int I have given as
a point cut
expression okay so at the aspect is
there in this class component and this
is the method like any method which got
match with this this method has to be
done before its
execution so now what I am doing
is here I am calling this
API now when I'm calling this API so
here if you
see currently
this this got matched no it has argument
string comma and does it taking any
argument no so no matching happen so it
will go inside it will run this the
statement employe util employ helper
method and it passing two parameters so
it is trying to invoke this
method so this method when a spring
board try to execute this method it will
check hey any point cut matches happen
so it will say that okay there is a
point cut which says that argument which
takes a string comma and any method
which takes the string
command
yes this
is applicable for this it got matched
with this point cut means this has to be
done and before so this will print first
inside before method
aspect then it will go inside this
employer helper method call and after
that it will return
this got it ask
right okay so now one question can comes
to that okay hey what if instead of uh
string in if we have object how we give
so we can give like ask and give the
proper class path of that class till
class level like
any object of this class com. concept
and coding do learning springboard do
employ right so it will match to any
method that accept a reference for this
class and there is something called at
theate ARS now whenever at theate comes
before this at theate means we have to
provide the path for The
annotation okay so how to read this is
matches any
method with particular parameter and
that parameter class is annotated with
particular annotation now here when I
give atate ask and this is The
annotation service so what I'm looking
for is here if you see atate ask and I
have given the path for service
annotation so what happen is it will
look for any
method any
method that accept one that accept
any argument
okay and that argument class
right has this annotation service
because see ask is deal with the
argument we don't have to worry about
the method name and all any method but
the argument which you are passing does
that argument has this that class has
this annotation so here the argument is
employ Dow let's say this and so this is
one method which is ultimately getting
invoked let's say and this me method has
argument employed Dow now this employed
Dow class had this annotation at theate
service so this got matched up okay so
AR deals with the argument and atate AR
says that the argument which you are
getting the Class Type does this has
this annotation if yes then only do the
matching with
this so This method has employed Dow and
this employed Dow has adate service
which got matched this with anotation so
this is a match for this point
cut okay this is the seventh type of
point cut which we can use matches any
method on a particular instance of a
class okay so here at theate aspect so
this is the class where we are writing
all the point Cuts so here I'm using
Target so Target is your one type of
point cut expression uh point cut type
so Target now here what we have to give
we have to give a till class level path
so this is my
class now whenever an instance of this
class is used to call any
method this will get
matched so just see this example in this
class very very simple class employee
rest controller expose this
API does this mapping
now I'm calling this
method
okay fetch employee it is running this
employ util do employ helper method so
now it will see that hey any point cut
match happen so here Target means says
that in the Target what is the class I
have given employee
util whenever this instance of this
class so this is an instance of this
class
is used to invoke a particular method
for that method this got matched
up so is it
clear and there is one more uh the
target flavor of this is like we can
even provide an interface also instead
of direct class instead of direct class
we can provide an interface so now here
if you see that this is the class
structure I have
created okay the controller class this
controller class has
dependent
on employee interface so I have created
one employee interface this employee
interface has two
child temp employee Perma employee
permanent employee so this has two type
of employees okay so you know already
that we have to use qualifiers properly
because if we have to use we have to
tell which dependency we it has to
be put inside this employee object
object okay and I am using that employee
object by calling the method if you see
this
aspect I writing a point cut for the
type Target and what I have
given till interface level I have given
this interface name so what this
interface name is
that any child classes for this
interface like if it is an instance of
Temple employee
or if it is an instance of permanent
employee doesn't matter because this is
an interface I have given right so no
matter whatever the child instance it
has this is applicable so now here if
you see that I am calling fetch employee
method employee on a temporary employee
object because I have put a qualifier
temp employee so it's I'm creating an
object of this so even though you are
creating an object of this temporary
employee this this point cut will get
matched because this is an interface so
for all its child instances also this is
valid so it will run this before calling
this method so I'm call use at theate
before so means it will run first this
inside before
method and then it will go inside fetch
employe method of a
temporary okay so only point to say that
when even if you use interface instead
of direct class now with interface no
matter how many child classes are there
of this
interface for that instance of those uh
child classes this will get true this
will get
match okay now we can also one more
thing is we can also combine two point
cut so we have seen multiple point cut
right which
one
execution
within at theate Within
asks at the rate
ARS Target and at the rate
annotation right so we have seen
multiple annotation multiple Point Cuts
we can combine them also we can use
together also using and and or Boolean
and Boolean or so here if you see that
this is one example which I am
giving I am writing one aspect class put
at the
aspect okay this is the method but this
is my point cut
expression so first is execution
execution means pointing to a particular
method return type is anything this is
the
package right so this is my
class dot any
method in this class any method any
return type and it do not accept any
argument okay
but now here if you see that I have
combined it with another point
cut now I'm adding and and means it's an
and both should get true then only this
will get match up and this will should
run at theate
within within is deal with till class
level so I have provided uh but I have
used at theate so means annotation path
I have to given so annotation path I
have given is rest controller so any
class which has this rest FR controller
annotation okay so this is one and this
is like similarly I have written for
R now let's see that if I call this
method if I call this what would happen
so now this uh you have invoke this now
spring boot will say that hey this
method got this method got match with
any aspect so first execution let's see
this
first any return type okay good com.
concept and coding. learning springboard
employ controller yes this is within
this package and the class
name any method name okay and uh this
method doesn't accept any argument yes
this got match so this is true this got
matched now
and any class which should have this
rest controller yes this class has rest
controller so this both get true means
this is got matched with for this method
and this should run and this should run
either before or after I have put at the
before so it will run inside before end
method aspect inside before end method
except okay so this is run and there is
another so it will see try to match it
with this
also
star so this got match up exactly same
so this is
true
or we should have at theate component
within means this class has at theate
component no this doesn't have at theate
component uh so this will get false but
since this is or anyone should get true
so this is also true so this is this
method also has to be run but it before
right so this will also get print inside
before or
method so now after this it will return
item
fetch there is one uh one more thing
called named point cut so in the name
Point part what we have seen this before
is we have used add theate before and
here we are used to give the point cut
expression so we can name that
expression so here this is the way of
giving so I'm put using at theate Point
Cod and give the
expression so we are telling springboard
that this is one point
cut okay just provide a method name
which should be empty we don't have to
write anything inside it the purpose of
this is that okay we are just giving the
name of this point cut to this one this
method name now this method
name custom Point custom point cut name
is now is the name for this
expression okay so now instead of using
this full expression again and again at
multiple places let's say you can just
use custom point cut name name like this
so this is how I used it atate before
now here if you see I have given custom
point cut name this
method now it will automatically use uh
change it with this expression
complete the bigger part is completed
point cut now the advice I think while
we were covering the point cut you
already know this it's an action which
is taken either before or after or
around the method execution
so we have seen this example right we
have currently learning this uh point
cut expression now the point cut we are
done now the something is advice so this
yellow part yellow part is known as
advice so once this point cut got
matched with any particular method after
that this has to be run this is known as
advice this advice has to be run either
before after or
around before is we have already seen
after is self-explanatory that okay
after that method invocation you have to
run this advice but what is
around around as the name says that it
surrounds the method execution before
and after
both and it's very little very minor
different from the before and after so
now let's check
this this is a point cut expression I
have given I think now you can read this
expression this is an execution which
has to match with a particular method
return type this is still class level
path and any method okay so in the
employee util any method any return type
which doesn't take any argument this
should get matched
up okay so say that this employee util
class any me uh any method because this
is star any return type and which
doesn't take any argument
so this should get matched with this
expression now once this is matched this
advice has to be run before after or
around I have tell around around means
it is possible that we can run something
before and after now see till now what
we are using is at the before or at the
rate after there what we have to do is
we have to just write
what we have
to run before or after okay so now in
the at theate before when we use at
theate before what generally happen is
it will simply execute this and
internally internally it will call the
method invoke the method if you are
using at theate after it will internally
first call the method and then execute
this advice
but in case of at theate
around we have to call the method so in
the
around we have to use this joint Point
proceeding joint point right so here in
this case do whatever you have to do
before the method use this joint point
and call proceed method you have to call
proceed method which will actually
invoke
your
method and then you can do certain task
after it so before then you invoke the
actual method and do some after work so
as the around says that it surrounds the
method execution before and after if you
need to perform any task you can do it
then actually you have to invoke this
method like this right it will take care
of calling your method and if you have
to do after task you can do this here so
atate around is also very
powerful advice which we can
use now you can ask me right hey Shan
how this adate proceed is actually
calling the method I will tell you how
internally it invokes also but first
thing is that where we are is
understanding what around
us okay join point is nothing but the
point where where we are actually
invoking the method your actual method
that generally in Spring spring boot aop
we call joint Point joint point it
generally considered a point where
actual method invocation happen that's
it so now we have seen lot of
information now one thing might be
bugging you as of today by now few
question we all should have how this
interception works I I understood what
is point
cut what is uh
advice right different types of point
cut I know different type of advice
before after around I know I got it uh
the matching happen with the point cut
and uh if the matching happen before
that actual method this advice will run
so either before this advice will run
and that method or after method this
advice will run or around it but how
this how this linking interception is
working and what if you have thousands
of point cut what if you have thousands
of point cut so whenever I am
particularly invoking a method I am
particularly invoking a method so if I
have thousands of point cut it is doing
matching with all the point Cuts one by
one by one will it
not causing a problem in
latency right so this question might be
be bugging you very much how this become
a so powerful tool if this is like too
much
complicated right so now let's
understand how aop internally
works I'll try to explain it in a very
simple manner this is a very huge
internally code based but I will explain
you a very simple method which will help
you to link
everything okay so be with
me so first when an application is
startup
happen okay I will also uh show you from
the code also but first let's understand
theoretically what is the step and then
we'll show from the code when you start
an application you know that spring boot
looks for the beans so here in the first
step it look for atate aspect annotation
classes so this is the
first now once the it found this classes
now it knows that it this class contains
point cut expression so the Second Step
what does it do is it Parts the point
cut expression parts means it simplifies
those expression save it in a particular
data structure so that it would be easy
to do a matching it will do a parts of
point cut
expression and stored in an efficient
data structure or Cache after
parsing the third step is
it look for atate component at theate
service at theate controller ET
annotation classes now at this point
once it is started looking for at theate
component at theate service all this
type of another beings it checked if it
is eligible for interception or not
based on the point cut
expression need not need not to be an
exact method level but at least it knows
that yes this class is valid for
interception right so for each class it
check it is eligible for interception or
not based on the point cut
expression and if yes it create a proxy
out of it right if yes it create a proxy
class either using jdk Dynamic proxy or
cglib code generation Library
proxy right so if you are writing this
class employe
util this is your class
it has one method called let's
say
fetch does
something right and during aspect and
point cut it matches
that and
during point cut it fetches it it check
that it is eligible for interception
right if you have used uh dot dot asress
now any class inside a package sub
package so definitely this will come
into the that
uh interception right
because any class inside this let's say
concept and coding package and sub
packages and this is inside that package
only so definitely it comes into this
radar so what it will do is it will
create a proxy of
it either using jdk Dynamic proxy or
cgli proxy so now there is
one employee
util some at theate some 5 4 3 2 1 some
random proxy class is
made right and what it does it it will
create a child class of it so now this
become your parent and this will create
one child
class okay and it will overwrite this
method atate public
void
Fetch and it will generate some so cglib
and Dynamic is like it will generate
some code now it will generate some code
which will call certain spring framework
so don't worry about this what what code
is there but I'll tell you that
understand this five step first first is
look for ad theate aspect classes pass
the point cut expression store it in an
efficient manner Now look for all the
other uh annotation
classes now check if those classes are
eligible for interception based on the
point cut expression if yes then create
a proxy of those classes using this
to you might be say when to use jdk
Dynamic proxy and when to use cgli so
generally is
like if your if your if your class is
already a child of interface let's say
employee
util implement this interface let's say
employee implements employee means there
is this class is already a child of any
interface then jdk Dynamic proxy is
used okay if this class is not a child
of any any interface then cgli is used
because this cglib has the capability to
create a
subass of a particular class jdk Dynamic
proxies just can create a new class and
use just implement interface so it's
automatically a child of this one but
cgli is like when your class is not a
child of any uh class then cglib is used
it can create a
subass okay now let's see
that
okay
first I am starting the application I am
starting the application now sh the code
so here if you see that I have created
one
aspa some logging aspa and I have one
before advice and after advice and this
is the point cut expression which I have
given right very very simple point cut
expression I've given execution which uh
matches with employee
util class any method any return type
right the same so in the before method I
am just printing inside before method
aspect and after method I am printing
inside after method aspect so this is
very simple aspect I have
created now here if you see that I am
starting the application
now so now I starting the application
now here if now here if you see the
first control goes to where the first
control goes to point cut parer so what
this actually does is that it will Parts
your expression
okay so this is the first Parts the
point cut expression it will goes to
your point cut parser class and here if
you
see all your point cut expression it
which resolve it into some simpler
understandable and efficient data
structure after
passing the control goes to to wrap if
necessary so here in this see now the
second is this
one the second control goes to in this
class Auto proxy Creator wrap if
necessary so here in this what happening
is it will check it will now it is going
through all the beans atate component at
theate uh service at theate rest
controller now it is checking hey does
it required
interception if yes then it is creating
a proxy of it it is creating a proxy of
it right if it if this class required if
this Bean required interception it
create a proxy of
it now if you go now I am proceeding
further now proximity created to either
jdk dynamic or cgli so this is the third
part
right so this one I haven't taken
screenshot but the proxy here you can
see in the code itself either here if
you see that jdk Dynamic aop proxy or if
in Target class do it is interface there
is no interface at all it goes for cglib
aop
proxy okay so till now what we have done
is and after
this I'm running
again so currently my class employee
util doesn't have any interface so it
goes for
cglib and here if you see that
application startup happen
successfully
okay so till now before application
start up it's clear what it is doing it
Parts the point
cut now after that when it is uh
creating the bean during application
startup for each class if it required
interception it create a
proxy so which proxy either jdk proxy or
uses cglib based proxy but it uses any
one of the proxy and create a proxy
class now for at this point of time
there's something called employee util
atate some random number now this is my
proxy class which is now a child of
employee
util and it has overed that method
whatever the method it had overed it
which required interception and now it
has written some code over there
generate code
now I am invoking the request which need
advice to be run now I am invoking this
API so controller now I am invoking this
method at this
point now what will
happen so here if you
see now let's see I am invoking a method
so now here I am
hitting okay so now what would happen
here at this time
we'll see that it it would have come
here and then call employee util do
fetch employee method now if I go
inside now it will
check at the point of application
startup for this employee util because
this is applicable for interception
there is one proxy class created for
this employee util proxy right so
internally that proxy class might have
invoked not this class involved that
proxy class got involved
because here if you see that my
aspect it matches it matches with this
uh employee U right it matches with this
so this class required interception and
during application startup employee util
at theate something a proxy class have
created so that proxy class have created
we can't put debuger point in that proxy
class because that is dynamically on fly
that proxy class is created
and in that proxy class what it does it
it
invoke
your intercept method inside cglib aop
proxy so here if you see inside
cglib it will invoke this intercept
method why cgli because employee util is
not a child class of any so that's why
cgli proxy have used at this point of
time at this point of time
this so This proxy might have been
used so that's why that employee util at
theate some proxy class have got invoked
and it has called this intercept
method now see this what this intercept
method is
doing there you will see that it is
creating a chain of
advice right so now let's say that this
method which we have to invoke there are
let's say
five point cut which are
matched so there is a list of Point Cuts
or advice now which has to be run for
this some could be before some could be
after or some could be around which has
to be run but this five got matched with
that particular method okay so now I
have created a chain not I the jdk
library I have has created a chain now
now what would happen is that it is
calling do proceed method so this
proceed method
goes to this reflection method
invocation this
proceed so now here if you see that it
has
counter so now let's say it has to run
five advice right so it will go 5 4 3 2
1 and after all the advice method
invocation has happened
okay but there could be some before
there could be some after so how it is
handling this I will tell you so
currently index is uh zero no index is
not zero what happen is it will go
inside this else
part okay so now let's say we have two
advice right I showed you we have before
and after here in the code I have showed
you the uh aspect which I have written
one is before and one is after which
matches
this okay so in the chain I have two
counter is
two right so now so it's starting with I
think it is starting with Plus+ so it is
starting with uh 0 1 right then it is
matching if the counter reaches to the
end so first let's say before is coming
so now what before is coming what it is
done is it is
invoking so for before there is a it
will invoke a method so first so first
call when it is calling Interceptor
method Interceptor right so before it
will call method before advice
Interceptor so this invoke will get
invoke and here it will say that it will
run the advice first advice do before it
is running the advice first okay so this
advice is running before so it will
print inside before method X expect
now so this has
printed inside before
method accept at this point at this
point now again it called do proceed mi.
proed method invocation do proceed so it
goes back to this
method now again the counter has already
reached to the Plus+ so it become one
now again it hasn't reached to the end
so what happen is it goes to the else
part now again this again calls invo but
now for the after
one it will call
third this Interceptor aspect J after
advice because now the advice is after
so it will call this Interceptor call
this invoke method now after is like
after the method advice should run so
that's why here it say that it
calls the back so now it is doing kind
of a recursion way if you know recursion
you can easily understand this it calls
the proceed again hey you proceed
further and once that proceed happen
then come back and run this advice after
okay so now it goes up
proceed fourth it again goes to this
proceed now control Plus+ it already
reach two so now this become equals now
here if you say that it is invoking the
joint point I I already told that join
point is a point where the actual method
invocation happen now it is actually
invoking the method so now it is
invoking so currently this after advice
it is will run currently it is in this
part so currently this is
running and when this is running invoke
joint point so fifth step this method
invocation will happen so this method
invocation actually happens means
this employee U this will print fetching
employee details will get
printed so it will
print fetching employee
details so this fifth is also completed
when this is completed and it returns so
it returns from where it comes so it
comes from this so after that it will
run so this will return now invoke
advice after one so now after advice
will run right so this is your actually
the sixth after advice so after advice
will run
means this is the
after inside after method
aspect inside after method aspect so
this will get printed like this so this
is your actual method which you wanted
but see before and after advice run
and how I told you right so here if you
see that currently if I debug it so
currently it is running inside
reflective method invocation so first it
is running
before so it will come under
your method before advice Interceptor so
once it has printed the advice by now
and then it call
proceed then again this method has been
invoked
then again this method has been invoked
now it will goes to uh after now in the
after it will first call
proceed and then it comes to this uh
method so it will again goes to that
method now it
will now it will call this actual
method now it will call the actual
method here now it say that uh actual
method has been invok inside the employe
util now after actual method it will go
again back to the advoice uh finally
part where the advice will run and
finally it will
print if it see the
console before employee and after if any
doubt we can discuss further and uh I
hope you will like it please do share it
with your friends who really confused
with the proxy and the aop part thank
you thank you bye